At the beginning, I motivated that
we look at these UML state diagrams.
And that many of the features that
they support are primarily intended for noting
diagrams compactly
and clearly, i.e.,
not having to specify flat
state diagrams with very many states.
This compactness also
has a counterpart.
Namely, you can also turn such
a compact UML state diagram back into
a flat state diagram
by tapping it flat.
Finally, I want to look at
that here, in three videos with examples.
You can take a
UML state diagram and
flat-knock that, resolving the composite
states (whether hierarchical or formed by
regions), and thereby get
equivalent flat state diagrams,
state diagrams that don't
use all these features.
Equivalent in the sense that
the semantics are the same,
that they allow
the same transitions.
So that basically you could have also
worked with this flat state diagram, but
you don't want to because then you
lose all these advantages of the compact representation.
Because in general, this flat
state diagram will just contain
a lot more
states and/or transitions.
This corresponds a bit to the transition
from Petri nets to their reachability graphs.
Where also the reachability graph to a
Petri net can be much larger, because
the Petri net is a
special compact way to represent behavior.
And you can look at
this in a similar way.
I'm not going
to do this formally.
We're just going to look at three
examples and use those to explain the
strategies that you should then be able to
apply to other examples, with the same features.
We're not going to look
at all the features of UML
state diagrams, nor all the ones
we've seen, or combinations of them.
Very
deliberately.
And of course, then for exercises and later
for the exam, you only need to be
able to apply yourself what occurs
here in the examples as well.
Let's do this
concretely for an example.
Here is a UML state
diagram, obviously not a flat
state diagram because it
uses such a hierarchical state.
What makes this example stand out, what's
still sort of fairly simple here compared to
what UML state diagrams might be overall,
is that no regions show up here.
So no region state, just
actually such a hierarchical state.
And there is also no
history used in this example.
In other examples in a
moment, it will be different.
What would be
the strategy here?
How can we make
this a flat state diagram?
Well, obviously we need
to remove this hierarchy.
We could say we just keep
the simple states A, B, C, D.
But of course that can't be it
yet, then we would somehow ignore or
lose in particular these entries and
exits to such a hierarchical state.
The basic idea will be to keep
the simple states (A, B, C, D will
just still show up in the
flat state space); these entries and exits
at the edge of such a
hierarchical state, those have to be translated.
So we just need to
know what that means, to
exit from such an
overall state with trigger E.
That means (we know that if
we would go back to the
corresponding slides) that we could come from C
as well as from D to A with E.
That is, this one transition here (in
the UML state diagram) must then become
two transitions in
the flat state diagram.
Namely one from C
and one from D.
So that's where we put in what we
know about the exits and also about the entries.
So also the entry of
A to this complex state.
Then we need to know, what
does such a standard entry mean?
That means that we would
take the starting state here.
I.e., it becomes directly a connection from
A to C in the flat state diagram.
There we will translate
what then these entries and
exits at the edge of
such a hierarchical state mean.
Transitions that have nothing
to do with this
hierarchy at all and that are
simply between simple sub-states, those are kept.
So that we can go
from A to B with f.
That's in the UML state diagram
and there are no hierarchies involved somehow.
That is, since we've kept these simple states A,
B, C, D, we can just keep transitions like
that that don't somehow involve
the edge of a hierarchical state.
Then we'd have everything covered except
for how to deal with start states.
What will be the starting state
of an associated flat state diagram?
And it can
only have one.
Unlike in the UML state diagram, where
there can be multiple starting states (namely in
different regions or different nesting levels), in
the flat one there can only be one.
And that, of course,
will be the outermost one.
Because this is the outermost start
state in the UML state diagram,
it also remains as the start
state in the flat state diagram.
However, this start state in this inner
nesting level, for example, will no longer
appear in the
flat state diagram.
It might be relevant for the translation
(i.e. the information that we would actually go
to C with this transition, which is a
standard entry, because this is the start state).
This information is used
in creating the start state.
But that node itself doesn't have to
show up in the flat state diagram then.
What
happens?
What would
be the statement?
The statement was, keep the simple states
(that's why we keep A, B, C,
D), translate the entries and exits
(we'll do that in a moment),
keep other transitions
between these states simple.
We can
do that already.
We'll keep, so to speak, the entrances
that on the one hand satisfy or
correspond to this starting state
here, the outermost starting state, but
also in particular those transitions that are not
somehow on the edge of such a hierarchical state.
So this one is kept, this
one is kept, these two are kept.
That explains why
we have these transitions.
And then we just have to translate the
transitions that have something to do with the
edge of a hierarchical state,
so this e-transition and this a-transition.
What is the
respective translation there?
For the
a-transition we know:
That was a standard entry
into this complex right state.
And we know that we just continue there
at the starting state from the inner level.
That was exactly the
connection that was there.
Then afterwards we can
also remove that marking
because it wasn't
on the outermost level.
So it doesn't remain in the flat
state diagram, but it should be used
to determine where we
go from A with a.
That's the translation
of this part.
And then we still have
to take care of e.
That's this transition that, yes, goes from
the edge of this complex state to A.
So those are these two transitions
that we have to translate exactly
so that you can get from C as
well as from D to this left state, A.
And then we would
have that completely translated.
This UML state diagram
becomes this flat state diagram
where there are
no more hierarchies.
It's just a
normal flat state diagram.
And the main step in the
concrete case here was to replace this
one transition that
led away from the
hierarchical state with several transitions
that start from the states.
That was the translation of this
one concrete transition from the edge.
We did something
with that one, too.
Namely, that was
a transition that
led to the default entry and
then led to C in the continuation.
We used that
here as well.
The basic strategy is to translate
all these entries and exits at
the edge of hierarchical states
appropriately, and keep the rest essentially.
As it
stands here.
This is the simplest case, because
it was also the first example.